Guide to the California Asian American Artists Biographical Survey Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
California Asian American artists biographical survey records
circa 1850-2007
SC0929
Stanford University
25 Linear feet
The collection contains biographical files on more than 1000 artists active in California between 1850 and 1965, biographical files for 91 artists not active in California, and reference files. Biographical files contain exhibition records, catalogs, press coverage, and examples of art work (in the form of slides or photographs); in some cases there is also correspondence and/or interviews. Some materials may be photocopies. The reference files contain similar materials but are arranged by subject. Because of date range of the project and the nature of immigration before the 1970s, artists of Chinese and Japanese ancestry predominate in these files.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The California Asian American Artists Biographical Survey Collection, was begun as a project of San Francisco State University in cooperation with the Smithsonian Institution’s Archives of American Art, and was initially funded in part by the National Endowment for the Humanities. The collection has been housed at Stanford University since 2003 as part of the Asian American Art Project directed by Gordon H. Chang and Mark Dean Johnson.
The materials found in the collection are the result of over ten years of work by researchers and students at San Francisco State University; the University of California, Berkeley; the University of California, Los Angeles; Sacramento State University; and Stanford University.
For a majority of these artists information is limited and may only consist of a listing in an exhibition catalog, a mention in a newspaper, or a record in an enrollment document for an art school. We were however able to amass significant information for 159 artists. Research sources consulted were primarily in English. Books, exhibition catalogs and other published materials regarding specific artists in other languages were translated when possible.
With 1965 as the cutoff date for this project, we have used the criteria that artists must have been actively exhibiting or studying in California by this time. Because of the date range of this project and the nature of immigration before the 1970s, artists of Chinese and Japanese ancestry predominate in these files, with artists of Filipino and Korean ancestry being fewer in number, and artists of other Asian ancestry not present at all.
Description of the Collection
The California Asian American Artists Biographical Survey Collection is composed of biographical files on more than one-thousand artists active in California between 1850 and 1965, as well as reference files, and a limited number of files on artists active outside of California. Materials were gathered during the research phase of the Asian American Art Project that culminated in the publication of the book Asian American Art: A History, 1850-1970, and the organization of the material reflects its use for this purpose. (Please see "Introduction to Biographies of California Asian American Artists, 1850-1965" in Asian American Art, A History: 1850-1970, for more detailed information regarding the research methods and criteria used to build this collection.)
The collection is composed of four series:
1. California Artists Files (entry artists)- files on 159 artists who are included in the biographical entries in Asian American Art: A History, 1850-1970.
Files contain a range of materials including photocopies of secondary biographical source materials, information from census records, photocopies of newspaper articles (including internment camp newspaper articles), photocopied materials from other repositories such as the Archives of American Art and the Oakland Museum of California, original documents, interview transcripts and some audiotaped interviews, and examples of artwork (ranging from photocopies to color reproductions). Some information appears in the form of spreadsheets or other compiled documents produced by project researchers, and related materials and original source materials can be found in series 4.Audiovisual materials and oversized documents have been pulled from files and appear at the end of this series.
Abbreviations used in descriptions for these files include:
FAMSF: Fine Arts Museums of San Francisco
CPLH: California Palace of the Legion of Honor, San Francisco
SFAI: San Francisco Art Institute (formerly know as the California School of Fine Arts)
LACMA: Los Angeles County Museum of Art
SFMOMA: San Francisco Museum of Modern Art
SFAA: San Francisco Art Association
2. California Artists Files (non-entry artists)-files on 1,222 artists not included in the biographical entry portion of Asian American Art: A History, 1850-1970.
Contents of files predominantly are photocopies of secondary biographical source materials, photocopies of newspaper articles, and spreadsheets or other compiled documents produced by project researchers, with related and original source materials found in series 4. In many cases a file in series 2 may only contain one document. There is no detailed description of the content of files in this finding aid.
3. Non-California Artists Files- files on 91 artists not active in California for a significant portion of their career.
Contents of files predominantly are photocopies of secondary biographical source materials, photocopies of newspaper articles, photocopied materials from other institutions, and spreadsheets or other compiled documents produced by project researchers, with related and original source materials found in series 4.
4. Reference Files.
These files predominantly contain materials than have been photocopied and place in individuals artist files. Within series 4 are descriptive sub-series such as "Schools," "Exhibitions and Exhibition Records," "Internment," "Artist Clubs," in which all pertinent information has been compiled.
Access Terms
Asian American art--19th century.; Asian American art--20th century.; Asian Americans--California.
Collection Contents
- California Artists Files (entry artists), Series 1
  Consists of files on 159 artists who are included in the biographical entries in Asian American Art: A History, 1850-1970. Files contain a range of materials including photocopies of secondary biographical source materials, information from census records, photocopies of newspaper articles (including internment camp newspaper articles), photocopied materials from other repositories such as the Archives of American Art and the Oakland Museum of California, original documents, interview transcripts and some audiotaped interviews, and examples of artwork (ranging from photocopies to color reproductions). Some information appears in the form of spreadsheets or other compiled documents produced by project researchers, and related materials and original source materials can be found in series 4. Audiovisual materials and oversized documents have been pulled from files and appear at the end of this series.
  - Alvarado, Ricardo Ocreto (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; materials related to Smithsonian Institution touring exhibition of artist's work. Ricardo Ocreto Alvarado was a photographer who documented the Northern California Filipino community in the 1940s and 1950s.
  - Aoki, Toshio (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; census records; newspaper articles; examples of artwork. Toshio Aoki was a painter who resided in Pasadena and San Francisco ca. 1900.
  - Asawa, Ruth (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; FAMSF exhibition information; SFAA exhibition information; exhibition catalogs; correspondence; images of artwork; resume; artist statement.
  - Asawa, Ruth - transcript of Archives of American Art interview (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bae, Yoong (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; small catalog from Asian Art Museum. Yoong Bae received a Ford Foundation grant to study in US in 1963, and lived in the Bay Area.
  - Bing, Bernice (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; resume; articles; correspondence; SFMOMA exhibition information; small publication on artist.
  - Carvajal, Sr., Carlos (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; newspaper articles; notes from family interview.
  - Chan, Eva Fong (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; records from Chinese Art Association, ca. 1935; SFAA exhibition information; FAMSF exhibition information; examples of artwork; interview with daughter.
  - Chang Dai-chien (Zhang Daqian) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; FAMSF exhibition information; photocopies of Ankrum Gallery info from Archives of American Art; photo of artist; newspaper articles.
  - Chang Shu-chi (Zhang Shuqi) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; information regarding Chinatown Artists Club-1944-45; misc. exhibitions records; FAMSF exhibition information; examples of artwork; newspaper articles; copies of exhibition brochures; catalog.
  - Chang Shu-chi (Zhang Shuqi) - exhibition catalog (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Exhibition catalog, Chinese Painting on the Eve of the Communist Revolution: Chang Shu-chi and his Collection, 2006.
  - Chang, Wah Ming (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; LA Times Index citation; biographical information from artist; book, The Life and Sculpture of Wah Ming Chang.
  - Chann, George (Chen Yinpi) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; information from artist's daughter; LA Times Index citation; Chinatown Artists Club-1944 information; examples of artwork; FAMSF exhibition information; Otis student information; SFAA exhibition information; resume; articles; correspondence.
  - Cheng Yet-Por (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; catalog; examples of artwork; resume; articles; images of artist.
  - Chinn, Benjamen (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Photocopies of biographical sources. SFAI enrollment information; examples of artwork; newspaper articles; catalog.
  - Choy, Katherine (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; photocopies from Oakland Museum records; FAMSF exhibition information; records from Newark Museum; articles; catalog.
  - Chun, David P. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; SFMOMA exhibition information; Chinatown Artists Club 1935, 1942-45 information; photocopies from Oakland Museum records; SFAA exhibition information; FAMSF exhibition information; examples of artwork; correspondence.
  - Chun, Sung-woo (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; SFMOMA exhibition information; photocopy of Whitney Museum's Young Americans exhibition catalog; FAMSF exhibition information; SFAA exhibition information; notes from interview with artist.
  - Date, Hideo (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; newspaper articles; LA Times Index citation; photocopies from internment camp newspaper, Heart Mt. Sentinel; misc. LA area exhib list; relocation camp departure index.
  - Duena, Victor (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; census records; articles.
  - Fong, Sr., Wallace H. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; census records; articles; copies of photos from the collection of the Chinese Historical Society of America. Wallace H. Fong Sr. was a photojournalist in SF c.1929-1940.
  - Fong, Wy Log (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; enrollment records, Portland Art School; city directory listings.
  - Foujioka, Noboru (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; photocopies of small brochures from 1927 CPLH-solo show and 1924 The Nippon Club, NY show; FAMSF exhibition information; enrollment records Portland Art School; newspaper articles; documentation of artwork in collection of FAMSF.
  - Fujikawa, Gyo (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; examples of children's book illustrations; articles.
  - Fujita, Sadamitsu Neil (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; FAMSF exhibition information; transcript of interview; manuscript of biography from artist; articles; correspondence.
  - Fujita, Sadamitsu Neil - interview transcript, correspondence (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Fujita, Sadamitsu Neil - manuscript of memoirs (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Fukuhara, Henry K. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; photocopies from internment camp newspaper, Manzanar Free Press; LA Times Index citation; relocation camp departure index; articles.
  - Gee, Yun (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; photocopies of Oakland Museum records; SFAI enrollment records; correspondence with artist's daughter; articles; catalogs; examples of artist's work.
  - Gee, Yun - correspondence with artist's daughter, slides (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Correspondence with artist's daughter (Li-lan).
  - Gee, Yun - photocopy of book, "The Paintings of Yun Gee" (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Harada, Taneyuki Dan (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; FAMSF exhibition information; interview transcript.
  - Hartmann, Sadakichi (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; articles; photocopied examples of artwork; photocopies of materials from UC Riverside Special Collections.
  - Hasegawa, Saburo (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; photocopies from Oakland Museum files; correspondence with artist's widow; small catalogs; articles; materials from family; photos of artwork.
  - Hashimoto, Michi (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; newspaper articles; census records; notes from conversation with artist's niece; LA Times Index citation; misc. exhibition citations.
  - Hayakawa, Miki (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; misc. exhibition records; FAMSF exhibition information; SFAI enrollment records;; articles; examples of artwork; translated article from Japanese newspaper.
  - Hayakawa, Sessue (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; articles.
  - Hee, Hon Chew (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; information regarding Chinatown Artists Club, ca. 1935; FAMSF exhibition information; SFAA exhibition information; articles; slide.
  - Hibi, George Matsusaburo (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; photocopies of internment camp newspaper, Heart Mt. Sentinel; misc. exhibition information; FAMSF exhibition information; SFAI enrollment records; relocation camp departure index; SFAI archival info; correspondence with artist's daughter; articles; photos of artwork.
  - Hibi, Hisako (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; relocation camp departure index; original cards and correspondence from artist; correspondence with artist's daughter; books; catalogs; photos; manuscript; slides.
  - Hibi, Hisako - slides, original greeting cards, "An Issei Woman's Story" manuscript (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Hibi, Hisako - correspondence regarding and transparencies for "Peaceful Painter: Memoirs of an Issei Woman Artist" book (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Hikoyama, Teikichi (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; misc. exhibition records; SFAA exhibition information; examples of artwork; articles; information provided by family in Japan.
  - Hiraga, Kamesuke (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; SFAI enrollment records; census records; information from Japan; articles.
  - Hodo Tobase (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; articles; correspondence from SFMOMA files. Hodo Tobase was a Zen priest who also taught calligraphy and had solo exhibition at SFMOMA in 1958.
  - Howe, James Wong (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; photocopies from artist's scrapbook at the Academy of Motion Pictures Arts and Sciences Library.
  - Howe, James Wong - articles (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Hsu, Kai-yu (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; materials from SFSU personnel file; articles; example of artwork.
  - Ikegawa, Shiro (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; SFMOMA exhibition information; misc. exhibition records; photocopies of Oakland Museum records; SFAA exhibition information; examples of artwork; notes from interviews with friends and family.
  - Inukai, Kyohei (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; census records; articles; examples of artwork.
  - Ishida, Nitten (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; articles; photocopies of photos. Nitten Ishida was a revered calligrapher during the post WWII period and was an important Buddhist abbot of the Nichiren Church in San Francisco.
  - Ishigaki, Eitaro (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; SFAI enrollment records; photocopies from Japanese publications and newspapers; articles; examples of artwork.
  - Ishii, Chris (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; correspondence with artist; articles; photocopies of photographs; photocopies of internment newspapers with illustrations; relocation camp departure index; Relocation center census sheet.
  - Ito, Miyoko (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; SFMOMA exhibition information; FAMSF exhibition information; SFAA exhibition information; photocopies of various Archives of American art papers that reference Ito; correspondence; articles; exhibition catalog.
  - Ito, Miyoko - catalog, copies of materials from Archives of American Art (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Includes transcript of Archives of American Art interview.
  - Iwata, Jack Masaki (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; Relocation center census sheet; relocation camp departure index; records of holdings at Japanese American National Museum, Los Angeles; newspaper articles; information from artist's wife; translations of Japanese articles.
  - Jayo, Federico Dukoy (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Photocopies of biographical sources.
  - Joe, Dale (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; FAMSF exhibition information; SFAA exhibition information; articles; photocopies of catalogs; artist's statement.
  - Kagi, Tameya (Box 7, Folder 10)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; misc. exhibition records, census records; translation of entry in Japanese book.
  - Kaneko, Jun (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; resume and other materials from artist; articles; notes from phone interview with artist; slides.
  - Kaneko, Jun - magazines, catalogs, brochures (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Kanemitsu, Matsumi Mike (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; photocopies of info from Japanese book; info on works held by LACMA; resume.
  - Kato, Taizo (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; info regarding album at Bancroft Library, UC Berkeley; census records; immigration records; city directory info.
  - Kee, Hu Wai (Key, H. W.) (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; SFMOMA exhibition information; and Chinatown Artists Club information; FAMSF exhibition information; SFAA exhibition information; info from daughter.
  - Kim, Ernie (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; California State Fair exhibition listings; FAMSF exhibition information; SFAA exhibition information; correspondence with artist's sister; many photographs of artwork.
  - Kim, Ernie - bound collection of photos and press (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Kingman, Dong (Box 8, Folder 8)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; Chinatown Artists Club information; misc. exhibition records; FAMSF list; Archives of American Art interview transcript; articles; catalogs; info from artist's son.
  - Kingman, Dong - Time, Fortune and Life magazine articles (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Kira, Hiromu (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; newspaper articles; census records.
  - Kishi, Masatoyo (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; FAMSF exhibition information; photos of artist; notes from interview with artist; resume; articles.
  - Kitagaki, Nobuo (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; SFMOMA exhibition information; SFAA exhibition information; photos of artwork; articles.
  - Kiyama, Henry Yoshitaka (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; SFAI enrollment records; SFAA exhibition information.
  - Kobashigawa, Hideo (Box 9, Folder 6)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; photocopies of internment camp newspaper, Manzanar Free Press; transcript of interview with family.
  - Kobashigawa, Hideo - book, Hideo Kobashigawa, A Kibei Artist's Life and Dream (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Book on artist published in Japan.
  - Kobayashi, Senko (Box 9, Folder 8)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; photocopies of info from Japanese publications including some translations.
  - Kotoku, Shiyei (Box 9, Folder 9)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; LACMA files; photocopies of publications from Japan (some translated); photocopies of SF Japanese newspapers (some translated); SFAA exhibition information; articles; materials from SF Japanese American History Archives including photocopies of photos and correspondence from artist.
  - Kuniyoshi, Yasuo (Box 9, Folder 10)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; LACMA files; photocopies of internment camp newspapers; misc. exhibition information; FAMSF exhibition information; SFAA exhibition information; articles; photocopied materials from Archives of American Art.
  - Kuraoka, David (Box 9, Folder 11)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; articles; resume; notes from interview with artist.
  - Kuwahara, Robert (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; photocopies of internment camp newspapers; Relocation center census sheet; relocation camp departure index; articles with examples of illustrations; census records.
  - Kwok, John (Box 10, Folder 2)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; SFMOMA exhibition information; photocopies from LACMA files; photos of artwork; photocopies of catalogs; misc. exhibition information including California Watercolor Society exhibitions; FAMSF exhibition list.
  - Lee, Chee Chin S. Cheung (Box 10, Folder 3)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; Chinatown Artists Club information; misc. exhibition records; FAMSF exhibition information; FAMSF exhibition information; SFAI enrollment records; SFAA exhibition information; photos of artwork; photocopy of biography in Calif Art Research Monographs; articles.
  - Lee, Chingwah (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; Chinese Digest articles; census records; obit.
  - Lee, George (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Lee, Jake (Box 10, Folder 6)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; Chinatown Artists Club information; misc. exhibition information; FAMSF exhibition information; SFAA exhibition information; articles.
  - Lee, Kem (Box 10, Folder 7)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; articles; photos of artwork taken at home of widow, Stella Wong.
  - Legaspi, Joaquin (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; SFAI enrollment records; census records; photocopy of publication in honor of Legaspi which includes his poetry.
  - Leong, Gilbert (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Photocopies of biographical sources; articles; examples of artwork; resume and other materials from artist's family.
  - Leong, James (Box 10, Folder 10)